L’Aerophile Collection
Science, Technology, & Business Division, Library of Congress
L’Aerophile Collection 1876-1949 (1893-1949)
Unclassed ST&B, TRS
152 boxes 15,000 items
Science, Technology, & Business Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, blueprints and manufactures information for early French and foreign aircraft and dirigibles, reports of accidents involving flyers and balloonists, World War I aerial photographs and intelligence reports, a series of French cartoons, drawings, graphs, charts, diagrams of equipment, maps, newspapers, printed material, and photographs. The materials in the collection were evidently assembled by staff of the magazine L’Aerophile which was published by Georges Besançon in collaboration with Union Aérophile de France. Subjects include aeronautics chiefly in Europe and the U.S., aeronautics corporations, air shows, aviators, balloons, bombs and missiles, commercial airlines, dirigibles, gliders, hydroplanes, medical aviation, military aeronautics, model aircraft, parachutes, propellers, record flights, and research and testing of aircraft. Individuals represented include Henry Harley "Hap" Arnold, Georges Besançon, Amelia Earhart, Charles Lindbergh, and William "Billy" Mitchell.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Arnold, Henry Harley, 1886-1950.; Besançon, Georges, 1866-1934.; Earhart, Amelia, 1897-1937.; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974.; Mitchell, William, 1879-1936.
Organizations
Union aérophile de France.
Subjects
Aerial photography.; Aeronautics in medicine.; Aeronautics, Commercial.; Aeronautics, Military.; Aeronautics--Caricatures and cartoons.; Aeronautics--Europe.; Aeronautics--Flights.; Aeronautics--France--Periodicals.; Aeronautics--Research.; Aeronautics--United States.; Aeronautics.; Air pilots.; Air shows.; Aircraft accidents.; Aircraft industry--Equipment and supplies.; Aircraft industry.; Airplanes--Design and construction.; Airplanes--Models.; Airplanes--Testing.; Airplanes.; Airships--Design and construction.; Airships--Testing.; Airships.; Balloonists.; Balloons--Design and construction.; Balloons--Testing.; Balloons.; Blueprints.; Bombs.; Gliders (Aeronautics); Hydroplanes.; Parachutes.; Projectiles, Aerial.; Propellers, Aerial.; World War, 1914-1918--Military intelligence.
Titles
Aérophile.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Collection purchased by Library of Congress in 1969.
Access
Request in Science, Technology, & Business Division reference desk, Adams Building, 5th Floor (ask for Tech Reports 202 707-5655)
Electronic Format
An enhanced Web presentation of the L’Aerophile Collection is available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://www.loc.gov/rr/scitech/trs/trslaerophile.html.
Background
In January 1893 the French journalist and balloonist Georges Besançon (1866-1934), in collaboration with the Union Aérophile de France, began publishing a monthly illustrated revue, L'Aerophile (published 1893-1947). Quickly, L'Aerophile became one of the premier journals of the early history of aviation. The first years were devoted to balloonists and the importance of meteorology on ballooning (for example, atmospheric effects on equipment, instruments, and humans). In later years, as artificial wings, gliders, man- and engine-powered planes were developed, the magazine brought their stories to the public. The materials in the collection were evidently assembled by staff of the magazine L’Aerophile.
Scope and Content Note
The fifteen thousand or so items contained in the 152 boxes of the Library of Congress collection include blueprints and manufactures' information of early French and foreign aircraft and dirigibles, reports of accidents involving flyers and balloonists, aerial photographs from World War I, and a series of French cartoons from the period 1909 - 1912 related to aviation. The collection also contains hundreds of photographs of early aviators and designers, including pictures of Charles Lindbergh and his wife Anne Morrow being feted in Paris during their European trip of 1933. A large number of L'Aerophile images appeared in the National Air and Space Museum's major exhibition in 2003 celebrating the centennial of the Wright brothers' first flight, titled the Wright Brothers & the Invention of the Aerial Age.
Series Description
The L'Aerophile Collection is arranged in six Series:
Publications and Reports
Corporations, 1920s-1940s
Photographs
Types of Aircraft
Motors and Engines
Aviators and Designers
http://lccn.loc.gov/2003682042
Container List
- Publications and Reports (Box 1-22)
  Early photographs, handbooks, catalogs, newspaper articles, blueprints, intelligence reports, and other publications relating to the early years of aviation, including balloon flight, airplanes and aviators.
  Arranged in boxes, folders, and envelopes.
  - Henry H. (Hap) Arnold Collection. (Box 1)
    - Arnold Collection. (Envelope 1)
      - Photograph of Curtiss Condors in Death Valley, California. (Item 1)
      - Photograph of an air mail delivery over a copper mine in Bingham, Utah. (Item 2)
      - Program for the ceremony that conferred the medal of merit to Jack L. Warner (Warner Brothers Studios), 1947 (Item 3)
    - New York Times article about young Henry H. Arnold, who later became the commanding general of the Army Air Forces (AAF) during World War II (includes photographs), 1926. (Envelope 2)
      - Signed photograph of Governor James Rolph Jr. of California at March Field. (Item 1)
      - Signed photograph of Charles Nungesser. (Item 2)
      - Photograph of A.L Welsh and H.H Arnold at Simms Station, Dayton Ohio, 1911. (Item 3)
      - New York Times article (reprinted from 1926) containing information on Major Arnold’s transfer from Washington. (Item 4)
    - A miscellaneous collection of black and white photos of the first aviation designers, philanthropists, test-pilots and first American aviators - Wilbur and Orville Wright, Thomas DeWitt Milling, Howard Hughes, etc. Pictures of first female aviators - Harriet Quimby, Amelia Earhart are also included. Early pictures of the U.S. Army Air Service (chiefs, pilots, crews and group pictures) and U.S. Army Air Corps in California, with Major Henry H. Arnold. (Envelope 3)
      - Photograph “Aero Club of Sweden”, 1911., (2 copies) (Item 1)
      - Photograph of the obverse of a bronze (rectangular) medal presented to the Wright Brothers in 1909., (2 copies) (Item 2)
      - Photograph of Charles Lindbergh with Mayor Dahlman of Omaha and Governor Adam McMullen of Nebraska. (Item 3)
      - Photograph of Amelia Earhart. (Item 4)
      - Photograph of Lt. Colonel Henry Arnold (commander of the western zone, Army Air Corps Mail Operation) with Governor Henry H. Blood of Utah and Mayor Louis Marcus of Salt Lake City. (Item 5)
      - Photograph of Hubert R. Harmon. (Item 6)
      - Signed photograph of Ben W. Olcott, Governor of Oregon 1919-1923. (Item 7)
      - Photograph “President Coolidge hears all about it from a Round-the-World flyer.” (Item 8)
      - Photograph of Major John H. Jouett. (Item 9)
      - Photograph of Harold Gatty and Wiley Post. (Item 10)
      - Photograph of President Coolidge, Lieutenant Lowell Smith and John W. Weeks, the Secretary of War, taken at Bolling Field (Washington D.C). “reception for world fliers, Sept. 9, 1924.” (Item 11)
      - Photograph “Round-the-World fliers,” featuring Lieutenants Leslie Arnold, Lowell Smith, President Coolidge, Secretary of War John Weeks, Lieutenant Leigh P. Wade, Erik Nelson and Henry H. Ogden. The photograph was taken in front of “The Chicago” in 1924 after the aviators had completed the first flight around the world. (Item 12)
      - Photograph of drawings of Anthony H.G Fokker, Igor Sikorsky, Captain Sir George Hubert Wilkins, Captain Roald Amundsen, Charles A. Lindbergh and Rear Admiral Richard E. Byrd. (Item 13)
      - Photograph of George Eastman (Eastman Kodak) “stepping out of Army photo plane shortly before his death.” (Item 14)
      - Photograph “Round the World fliers, 1924.” (Item 15)
      - Three photographs of the round the world fliers. (Item 16)
      - Photograph of “Ens. A.J Williams ... winner of the Pulitzer trophy – 243 m.p.h.” (Item 17)
      - Photograph of Colonel Thomas DeWitt Milling, U.S Air Service. (Item 18)
      - Photograph of LT. COL. C.E. Duncan. (Item 19)
      - Photograph of Captain E.H Beebe. (Item 20)
      - Photograph of Major Ray A. Dunn. (Item 21)
      - Photograph of Major S.E Brown. (Item 22)
      - Photograph “G.H.Q. Staff 1st Wing, March Field, Calif.” (Item 23)
      - Photograph of Major General Mason M. Patrick, Chief of the Army Air Service. (Item 24)
      - Photograph of Jimmy Doolittle, 1925. (Item 25)
      - Photograph of the Wright Brothers during the Ft. Myer tests. (Item 26)
      - Photograph of the round the world fliers, 1924. (Item 27)
      - Signed photograph of “Col. E. Wittenmyer” 1921. (Item 28)
      - Photograph “Class of 1925 Army Industrial College.” (Item 29)
      - Photograph of Colonel Billy Mitchell, 1922. (Item 30)
      - Photograph of Major General W.L Kenly, “Chief of Air Service.” (Item 31)
      - Signed photograph of Major General W.L Kenly. (Item 32)
      - Photograph of “Air Corps Officers at Marshall Field in Flying Equipment.” (Item 33)
      - Reproduced photograph of “Miss Harriet Quimby.” (Item 34)
      - Photograph “The general and his gang – 1920” Billy Mitchell. (Item 35)
      - Group Photograph featuring Lt. Wells, Lt. Batten, Lt. Harris Chief, Lt. Pearson, Lt. Barksdale, Lt. Johnson, Mr. Meister, Mr. Lockwood, Lt. Doolittle, Lt. Brookley and Lt. Macready. (Item 36)
      - Photograph “Howard Hughes and his round-the-world, record-breaking crew.” (Item 37)
      - Signed photograph (contemporary reproduction) featuring William Howard Taft, Wilbur and Orville Wright, Katharine Wright, Alan Ramsay Hawley, Herbert Parsons and others. The picture was taken at an award ceremony held for the Wright brothers after their return from Europe in 1909. (Item 38)
      - Approximately fifty unidentified photographs of Henry Arnold and others, soldiers and staff of the Army Air Corps and other famous aviators. (Item 39)
      - Booklet “The H.H Arnold Collection”, (3 copies) (Item 40)
  - Auction catalogs for ballooning-related items; 1934, 1935, 1940. (Box 2)
    - “Collection dite Au ballon" by M.Leon Bartou, “Paris. 8-9-10 Mai 1935.” (Item 1)
    - Aerostation: a catalogue of books and engravings illustrating the evolution of the airship and the aeroplane to 1938. Maggs Bros.Ltd, London. 1940. (Item 2)
    - Aeronautik: auction catalog in German illustrating items such as coins, porcelain, small books, fans, etc., with images related to aviation. Luzern, Schweiz. 26-27 June 1934. (Item 3)
  - Calendars (German aircraft manufacturers) 1926-1935. (Box 3)
    - Twelve German sheet calendars depicting airplanes. (Item 1)
  - Aerial photographs, worldwide, 1890s to 1940. (Box 4)
    - France: Aerial Photographs 1930-1940. (Envelope 1)
      - Aerial photograph of Reims. (Item 1)
      - Arial photograph of Paris. (Item 2)
      - Two unidentified aerial landscape photographs. (Item 3)
    - France: Aerial Photographs, Dates Unknown. (Envelope 2)
      - Photograph of an early glider. (Item 1)
      - Aerial view of a balloon competition. (Item 2)
      - Aerial view of Roman ruins. (Item 3)
      - Two aerial photographs of Tozeur, Tunisia, taken by Henry Farman. (Item 4)
      - Two aerial photographs taken by Henry Farman over Tunisia. (Item 5)
      - Le palais du Bey in Tunis, Tunisia. (Item 6)
      - Courcelles-Epayelles - a good aerial view of a French village. (Item 7)
      - Statute of Liberty, New York. (Item 8)
      - Aerial view of le Parc Bordelais. (Item 9)
      - Aerial view of the Sacré-Cœre Basilica, Paris (while under construction; completed in 1914). (Item 10)
      - Aerial view of Guadalajara, Mexico (taken from a balloon, pre-Revolution). (Item 11)
      - Aerial view taken from a balloon of a French regiment. (Item 12)
      - Ten unidentified aerial photographs of French cities and countryside. (Item 13)
    - Germany: Aerial Photographs. (Envelope 3)
      - Flugplatz Johannisthal - Germany's first airfield. (Item 1)
      - Two aerial views of Vienna, Austria. (Item 2)
    - Spain: Aerial Photographs. (Envelope 4)
      - Madrid: Puerta del Sol. (Item 1)
      - Madrid: Palacio Real. (Item 2)
      - Madrid: Sierra de Guadarrama, (3 photographs) (Item 3)
      - Spanish aerial view. (Item 4)
    - Switzerland: Aerial Photographs. (Envelope 5)
      - Three aerial views of Salzburg, Austria. (Item 1)
      - Aerial view of Mörsburg, Switzerland. (Item 2)
      - Aerial photograph of a canyon taken by the “U.S Army Air Service.” (Item 3)
      - Thirty-three unidentified photographs of Swiss cities, countryside and the alps taken by balloon. (Item 4)
    - Italy: Aerial Photographs. (Envelope 6)
      - Four photographs of early glider and kite experiments. (Item 1)
      - Photograph of an early airplane taking off. (Item 2)
      - Aerial view of Axis aircraft in Castelvetrano, Sicily 1942. (Item 3)
      - Thirteen unidentified aerial photographs. (Item 4)
    - Aerial View of Girard College. (Envelope 7)
      - Balloon view of Girard College, Philadelphia, (Samuel A. King, aeronaut). July 4, 1893. (Item 1)
    - Balloon Views of San Diego City's Harbor. 1923. (Envelope 8)
      - Two balloon views of San Diego City’s Harbor. (Item 1)
    - Aerial view of countryside and cities in France, Germany and Switzerland. 1890-1910. (Envelope 9)
      - Photograph of a balloon competition, 1908. (Item 1)
      - Five aerial views of Paris, including a photograph of Notre Dame, 1907. (Item 2)
      - Photograph of the French countryside (Fougerolles), 1908. (Item 3)
      - Aerial view of Angers Cathedral (scaffolding on front façade). 1909. (Item 4)
      - Aerial view of Angers, France. (Item 5)
      - Three unidentified aerial views. (Item 6)
      - Four aerial photographs (taken from an early airplane) of the Seine River mounted on cardboard with six additional aerial photographs that were once attached by paperclip. (Item 7)
    - Aerial Views Before the War. (Envelope 10)
      - Aerial view of the “Parc de l’Aero Club.” (Item 1)
      - View of a solar eclipse taken from a balloon. (Item 2)
      - Aerial view of the Eiffel Tower. (Item 3)
      - Two aerial views of Versailles. (Item 4)
      - Photograph “Les Alpes Tennengebirge.” (Item 5)
      - Aerial view of Moutfort, Luxembourg. (Item 6)
      - Aerial view of the park and hangar of l’Aero Club. (Item 7)
      - Aerial photographs of Paris (Eiffel Tower in distance)., (2 photographs) (Item 8)
      - Three aerial photographs of “Zodiac III” in Bétheny, France. (Item 9)
      - Two aerial photographs of a balloon contest in Aquitaine. (Item 10)
      - Two aerial views of Paris featuring the Eiffel Tower and the Arc De Triomphe. (Item 11)
      - Postcard with aerial photograph taken by Lucian Demazel. (Item 12)
      - Two aerial views of the Eiffel Tower (one taken directly overhead). (Item 13)
      - An envelope containing eleven photographs of a balloon voyage following a balloon contest in Paris. (Item 14)
      - Aerial view of Versailles taken by Andre Schelcher in the balloon “Zodiac.” (Item 15)
      - Aerial view of the Seine, Paris with view of the French Statue of Liberty. (Item 16)
      - Aerial photographs of Lyon, France, 1901., (2 photographs) (Item 17)
      - Aerial photograph of Amiens Cathedral with airplane in the distance, 1910. (Item 18)
      - Aerial view of one of the legs of the Eiffel Tower. (Item 19)
      - Photographs pertaining to night flight (illuminated airplane), 1912., (5 photographs) (Item 20)
      - Photograph of Henry Farman’s airplane at a stopover in Tozeur, Tunisia. (Item 21)
      - Aerial photograph of Reims cathedral taken from a dirigible. (Item 22)
      - Aerial photograph of the Place Pigalle, Paris, 1894. (Item 23)
      - Aerial photograph of Winterthur, Switzerland, 1901. (Item 24)
      - Unidentified aerial views, including photographs of cities, countryside, sunrises/sunsets, balloon contests, mountain ranges, clippings from l’Aérophile and postcards., (91 items) (Item 25)
    - Worldwide Aerial Views, 1920-1937. (Envelope 11)
      - Photograph of an ancient amphitheater. (Item 1)
      - Six photographs of the Rhône Alps. (Item 2)
      - Three aerial views of the Château de Chantilly. (Item 3)
      - Aerial view of the Château de Champlâtreux. (Item 4)
      - Aerial view of the Vaux le Vicomte. (Item 5)
      - Aerial view of the Rochefort en Yvelines. (Item 6)
      - Aerial view of the Château de Chalain "Lac du Chalain.” (Item 7)
      - Aerial view of the Château d’Ecouen. (Item 8)
      - Two Aerial views of the Château de Méréville. (Item 9)
      - Aerial view of the Château de Vallière in Mortefontaine, France. (Item 10)
      - Aerial view of a “runway and village” near Zinder, Niger. (Item 11)
      - Aerial view of Niamey, Niger. (Item 12)
      - Aerial view of an airfield near Zinder, Niger. (Item 13)
      - Aerial view of Lake Chad. (Item 14)
      - View of the ruins of Colysée in Rome with planes flying overhead. (Item 15)
      - Aerial view of Rab Island, Croatia overlooking the Adriatic Sea. (Item 16)
      - Aerial view of Niamey, Niger. (Item 17)
      - Two aerial views of Lake Chad. (Item 18)
      - Aerial view of Dubrovnik, Croatia. (Item 19)
      - Aerial view of Paris with airplane overhead (view of Arc De Triomphe in the far left corner). (Item 20)
      - Aerial view of the Tigris River near Baghdad. (Item 21)
      - Aerial view of Carcassonne, France. (Item 22)
      - Aerial view of Mont Saint-Michel, France. (Item 23)
      - Photograph taken from an airplane of Mt. Etna, an active volcano in Sicily. (Item 24)
      - Photograph taken from an airplane of Mont Blanc, the highest peak in Western Europe, 1928. (Item 25)
      - Two photographs of the first passage of the Alps by floatplanes. (Item 26)
      - Aerial photograph of “Ruines du Djebel de Zagora” (ruins in the Sahara desert). (Item 27)
      - Aerial photograph of elephants in Chad, 1936-1937. (Item 28)
      - Aerial view of the Pyramid of Zoser, Egypt. (Item 29)
      - Aerial view of “lac à Los Angeles.” (Item 30)
      - Aerial view of Versailles, 1936. (Item 31)
      - Aerial view of Ouargla, Algeria, 1934. (Item 32)
      - Aerial view of Lake Victoria. (Item 33)
      - Aerial view of planes flying over Paris in celebration of Bastille Day with a clear view of the Eiffel Tower. (Item 34)
      - Thirty-nine unidentified photographs. (Item 35)
  - Publications, USA: A-E. (Box 9)
    - Liberty Engine Service Bulletins. November, 1918. (Envelope 1)
      - Liberty Engine Service Bulletins (1-9) issued by the War Department Bureau of Aircraft Production, November and December 1918, (2 copies) (Item 1)
    - Notes on Liberty Engine Ignition System. 1919. (Envelope 2)
      - Notes on Liberty Engine Ignition System, issued by the Navy Department Bureau of Steam Engineering, 1919. (Item 1)
    - Manual for Balloon Cutters. October, 1918. (Envelope 3)
      - Manual for Balloon Cutters, issued by the War Plans Division, October 1918. Translated from a French document prepared by the Military Intelligence Division of the General Staff. The manual details proper care and handling procedures for balloon maintenance, (2 copies). (Item 1)
    - “History of the 96th Aero Squadron - First American Day Bomb Bardment.” (Envelope 4)
      - “History of the 96th Aero Squadron – First Americans Day Bomb Bardment. Prepared under the supervision of the commanding officer of the division, Captain James A. Summersett, Jr. November, 1918.” (Item 1)
    - History of the 96th Aero Squadron #2. (Envelope 5)
      - Additional copy of History of the 96th Aero Squadron. (Item 1)
    - Ercoupe, the instruction manual. June 1946. (Envelope 6)
      - Instruction manual and three brochures for the Ercoup, “The Certified Spin-Proof Plane” 1946. The brochures appeal both to business executives and farmers and describe the plane as “a practical modern necessity.” (Item 1)
    - The Ambassador, a brochure about the first modern civil aircraft, its features and specifications. Hampshire, England. July, 1948. (Envelope 7)
      - Descriptive brochure for the Airspeed Ambassador. (Item 1)
    - Civil Aviation: Industry Studies - Report of the Air coordinating committee, Washington DC. 1947. (Envelope 8)
      - Bibliography on Airports, produced by the Civil Aeronautics Authority, 1939. (Item 1)
      - References on Airports and Seaplane Bases, produced by the Department of Commerce Civil Aeronautics Administration, 1940. (Item 2)
      - A Selected and Annotated Bibliography in Aviation Education for Guidance Counselors, produced by the Department of Commerce Civil Aeronautics Administration Office of Aviation Training, 1946. (Item 3)
      - Airport Literature: A Selected Bibliography, produced by the Department of Commerce Civil Aeronautics Administration Office of Aviation Information, 1947. (Item 4)
      - References on Airports and Seaplane Bases, produced by the Department of Commerce Civil Aeronautics Administration, 1941. (Item 5)
      - Pamphlet: Civil Air Patrol, issued by the Office of Civilian Defense, 1941. (Item 6)
      - Report of the Air Coordinating Committee 1947, with attached letter from William C. Foster to President Truman, 1948. (Item 7)
      - Report prepared by the Transportation Division and issued by the Industrial Reference Service, U.S Department of Commerce entitled “Air-Cargo Potentials between the U.S and Cuba,” November 1946. (Item 8)
      - Report prepared by the Transportation Division and issued by the Industrial Reference Service, U.S Department of Commerce entitled “Air-Cargo Potentials between the U.S and The Republic of Panama,” December 1946. (Item 9)
      - Analysis of the Air Transportation Industry by Henry Beecken of Granbery, Marache & Lord, 1942. (Item 10)
    - Article: “New Altimeter Records Elevation of Plane Above Actual Ground” news release from the United Air Lines News Bureau. (Envelope 10)
      - Press release: New Altimeter Records Elevation of Plane Above Actual Ground. Released by United Air Lines. (Item 1)
    - Martin Model 167W. (Envelope 11)
      - Article: Martin Model 167W. (Item 1)
    - Magazine (U.S) The Aeroplane, November 30, 1945. (Envelope 12)
      - Magazine: The Aeroplane, November 30, 1945. (Item 1)
  - Publications, USA: F-N. (Box 9A)
    - The F-5L Flying Boat Handbook, Navy Department: Bureau of Construction and Repair. December, 1918. (Envelope 1)
      - The F-5L Flying Boat Handbook, Navy Department: Bureau of Construction and Repair. December, 1918. (Item 1)
    - Statements Issued from the Public Relations Office: The De Havilland Enterprise. “The Geoffrey De Havilland Trophy” and “Over the Counter Gipsy Engine Replacement.” (Envelope 2)
      - Statement issued from the Public Relations Office: The De Havilland Enterprise, “The Geoffrey De Havilland Trophy” 1948. (Item 1)
      - Statement issued from the Public Relations Office: The De Havilland Enterprise, “Over the Counter Gipsy Engine Replacement” 1948. (Item 2)
    - Handbook on the “CC” Interrupter Gear, Engineering Division Air Service. (Envelope 3)
      - Handbook on the “CC” Interrupter Gear, Engineering Division Air Service 1920., (2 copies) (Item 1)
    - Handbook of Instructions for Airplane Designers, 1923. (Envelope 4)